<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-04T13:10:45-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">‘Tine Zekis</title><subtitle>'Tine Zekis (she/her) is a software engineer, speaker, and advocate for Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion in Tech. This site contains a collection of content produced by 'Tine. Find her blogs, slides, videos, and more.</subtitle><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><entry><title type="html">Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html">&lt;p&gt;
  Welcome to Part III of a three-part series on &lt;em&gt;Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast&lt;/em&gt;. In this section, we will go over ways to fight off Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part I: Origin Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part II: Warning Signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This series is adapted from a talk I gave in 2019 at &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.musiccitytech.com/&quot;&gt;Music City Tech&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://fallexperiment.com/creamcitycode/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://techbash.com/&quot;&gt;TechBash&lt;/a&gt;. You can find the slides from that talk &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/tinezekis/impostor-syndrome-slaying-the-beast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can watch the talk I gave at TechBash &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ABv-toKt2Y&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you have not yet read parts I and II of this series, you can check those out here: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I imagine that you are reading this because you have experienced some amount of Impostor Syndrome in your life. So, now what? It's time for our fight scene!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-fight.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, holding up fists as if to fight&quot;&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-godzilla.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin, dressed in a Godzilla costume and kicking over a building&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Let's talk about how to slay the beast of Impostor Syndrome. We're going to cover various tools you can use, so hopefully you'll have a few powerful weapons in your arsenal to reach for whenever you need them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Track Your Accomplishments and External Praise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  When tracking your accomplishments, focus on what you did, not just the outcome. For example, we don't want to simply say, &quot;I got the job.&quot; Our Impostor Syndrome can easily turn that into, &quot;I somehow tricked them into giving me the job,&quot; or, &quot;I must have just been lucky.&quot; Instead, I would log something like this:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I successfully completed the code challenge&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In the in-person interview, I answered questions thoughtfully and thoroughly&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I nailed the data modeling whiteboard exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Don't forget to review these once in a while. I started logging my accomplishments a while ago, and at some point realized that I was never taking the time to look back at them. It might be helpful to set up a weekly reminder or develop some other system to regularly review the awesome things you've done.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  There are other great benefits to logging your accomplishments. They can be a helpful guide when it comes time to advocate for a promotion or a raise. It's also very handy when you need to update your resume or portfolio. You might find a few points that you completely forgot about, but decide you actually want to highlight on your resume.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Now let's talk about tracking external praise. Take note of every compliment or positive feedback you receive. Be sure to include the source of the feedback. Consider also jotting down how you felt about the compliment. Did you believe it? Did it make you uncomfortable to hear? It may be easier to simply identify your behavior: How did you &lt;em&gt;respond&lt;/em&gt; to the compliment? Did you accept it? Did you contradict it?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Once in a while, review this log and see what trends you notice. Perhaps there are certain areas about which you consistently receive positive feedback. Also look for trends in your responses. As you track the experience of getting this kind of feedback, you can start to be intentional about how you respond to it, disrupting your instinct to contradict or disregard positive feedback.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Catalog Your Skills&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-the-best.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with short, black and pink hair, smiling and holding up a plaque that says, You're the Best&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It can be a helpful exercise to list out your skills, the assets you bring to your current role (or to the role you're going for next). Sometimes it helps to think about your past experiences as a guide here. How were you able to be successful in your previous roles, or in school?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Maybe you're good at &lt;strong&gt;studying new concepts&lt;/strong&gt;. Or you've worked in &lt;strong&gt;customer service&lt;/strong&gt; and you've developed excellent &lt;strong&gt;communication skills&lt;/strong&gt;. Maybe you're a musician and you're great at &lt;strong&gt;pattern recognition&lt;/strong&gt;. Or you've done work with &lt;strong&gt;creative problem-solving&lt;/strong&gt;. Or maybe your previous work has helped you to master the art of &lt;strong&gt;persuasion&lt;/strong&gt;. These kinds of transferrable skills make you an invaluable asset to any team.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Then, be sure to stress these skills in your interviews. And try to hold them in your mind as you go about your day-to-day. You are an asset to your team, and to your company. This applies even if you're brand new to the industry, or to your role. Being new is an asset. You're a fresh pair of eyes on the code. You can ask questions no one else has because, &quot;Well, that's just how we've always done things.&quot;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Assemble Your Hype Squad!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, so what is a Hype Squad? A Hype Squad is a group of people who are in your corner, helping to support you. They listen when you need to vent. They build you up when you need confidence in yourself, and they push you when you need encouragement. If you don't yet have this group of friends, try to network at meetups, conferences, and other events. I bet there's someone at one of those events who would love to grab coffee or lunch with you and start learning about how awesome you are…so they can remind you about it later.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Build Up Others&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-you-got-this.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and pink hair, cheering and holing up a sign that says, You Got This&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Obviously, it will be your job to help out the other members of your squad. But let's go beyond that for a moment.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  There is great value in becoming a mentor to others. When you talk to someone who is somewhere along the path you've already traveled, you'll learn that you know a lot more than you realized. You will also start to see how valuable your experiences are to someone else, and how far you've actually come on your journey. And remember that for all of us, it's important to continue to normalize Impostor Syndrome. For someone who may be struggling with their own Impostor Syndrome, you can help by reminding them that they aren't alone.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Speaking of mentors, I'd like to take a moment to tell you about a man named &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jeffery-smith-devops/&quot;&gt;Jeff Smith&lt;/a&gt;. He's the head of ProdOps at my company, and he's one of those people who seem to be the go-to person for literally everything. Though, he seems to trust his team and give them autonomy as well. He's an awesome, engaging speaker, and he's currently writing a book. Not only do I look up to him, but as one of the only other black people in our tech department, he has been there for me when I need to talk about something awful in the news, like the state-sanctioned murder of a black man by police. He has reminded me that it's okay to call in black once in a while if I need to.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I think of Jeff as someone who's made it. So, the day I heard him casually refer to his own Impostor Syndrome, I was floored. If &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; deals with Impostor Syndrome, then maybe I'm not as unimpressive as I think I am.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Embrace Impostor Syndrome&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-hell-yeah.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person brown skin and short, black and pink hair, erupting from a volcano with text that says, Hell Yeah!&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This is one of the best tweets I've read this year:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Embrace imposter syndrome.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Revel in the fact you have fooled everyone.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You are a Trickster Goddess.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You are the Imposter Child for Deception and Clever Ruses.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; i&amp;#39;m a skELIton (@EliLizzieLizbet) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/EliLizzieLizbet/status/1107124546182832128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 17, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I'm sure you've heard the old adage to &lt;em&gt;fake it 'til you make it&lt;/em&gt;. Well, for those of us with Impostor Syndrome, there may not be a clear concept of what &quot;making it&quot; looks like. So, let's keep being really good at faking it! It's important to understand that no one really knows what they're doing. Don't let the people with an unearned sense of confidence fool you into thinking they know more than you do. They just know how to look good…and so do you!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Call to Action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So, what's next? It's time for our call to action! What are you going to do differently, starting tomorrow?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you've decided to start logging your accomplishments, external praise, or skills, go ahead and &lt;strong&gt;create that document&lt;/strong&gt;. Maybe it's and Excel sheet, or a Google Doc. Just figure out where you're going to keep track and make it happen.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;strong&gt;Reach out to someone&lt;/strong&gt; you think should be in your Hype Squad. Ask to grab coffee or drinks and catch up.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Remind yourself of &lt;strong&gt;how good you are at coming across as a badass&lt;/strong&gt;. There's a reason people think you're great. Try to remind yourself of that every day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-affirmation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with short, black and pink hair, smiling into a mirror above the text, Today is gonna be great!&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Remind yourself of &lt;strong&gt;your unique skills&lt;/strong&gt;. What do you have that no one else on your team does?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Try to &lt;strong&gt;view yourself through the eyes of your Hype Squad&lt;/strong&gt;, or through the eyes of the people who hired you after your awesome interview, or who promoted you after you kicked butt in your job all year. It's possible that they see something that you don't…try to see it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  And finally, &lt;strong&gt;practice the act of confidence&lt;/strong&gt;. They say that just by smiling or laughing, you can make yourself start to feel happy. So why not start acting confident? Speak up in your next meeting. Raise your hand for that challenging task you want (and say no to the administrative task you're not interested in). Walk into your next interview or daily standup like you own the room. And if you're worried this won't come naturally, I find it's best to take it at a bit of a strut.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-strut.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, posing on a fashion runway&quot;&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Thanks for reading! For the rest of the series, check out the two previous posts:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part I: Origin Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part II: Warning Signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Special thanks to all the people who made and released these awesome resources for free:
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Images by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bitmoji.com/&quot;&gt;Bitmoji app&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/bitmoji/bfgdeiadkckfbkeigkoncpdieiiefpig&quot;&gt;Chrome plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Impostor Syndrome definition paraphrased from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Research by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;Pauline Rose Clance, Ph.D., ABPP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Kimberlé Crenshaw on intersectionality by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality&quot;&gt;Columbia Law School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Quotations by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instyle.com/celebrity/stars-imposter-syndrome&quot;&gt;InStyle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/author/quotes/3503.Maya_Angelou?page=9&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Impostor Syndrome warning signs by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.powerofpositivity.com/11-signs-you-have-impostor-syndrome-and-how-to-fix-it/&quot;&gt;Power of Positivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to Part III of a three-part series on Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast. In this section, we will go over ways to fight off Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series: Part I: Origin Story Part II: Warning Signs Part III: Fight Scene</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html">&lt;p&gt;
  Welcome to Part I of a three-part series on &lt;em&gt;Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast&lt;/em&gt;. In this section, we will discuss the origin of the term and the initial research carried out on Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Part I: Origin Story&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part II: Warning Signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This series is adapted from a talk I gave in 2019 at &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.musiccitytech.com/&quot;&gt;Music City Tech&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://fallexperiment.com/creamcitycode/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://techbash.com/&quot;&gt;TechBash&lt;/a&gt;. You can find the slides from that talk &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/tinezekis/impostor-syndrome-slaying-the-beast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can watch the talk I gave at TechBash &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ABv-toKt2Y&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Oh, hey! My name is Christine Zekis, but I go by 'Tine Zekis, which also happens to be my Twitter handle (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tinezekis&quot;&gt;@tinezekis&lt;/a&gt;) My pronouns are she, her, hers, and I'm a software engineer…and an impostor.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-hi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, smiling and waving&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: Hi!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Before we dig in, let's start with a definition: what is Impostor Syndrome? Impostor Syndrome is a thought pattern in which a person diminishes their own accomplishments, often attributing their successes to luck. This is coupled with a fear of being discovered to be a &quot;fraud&quot;, or less capable than they appear to be. (Paraphrased from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-worst-trophy.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with short, black and pink hair, smiling and holding up a trophy that says, You're the Worst&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: &quot;You're the Worst&quot; Trophy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Origin Story&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  What we now call Impostor Syndrome was originally coined as the Impostor Phenomenon by two badass lady psychologists, Dr. Pauline Rose Clance and Dr. Suzanne Imes. In 1978, the conducted a &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; on &amp;mdash; and coined the term &amp;mdash; the impostor phenomenon amongst high achieving women. Incidentally, they're both still practicing in Atlanta, helping people cope with Impostor Syndrome, among other things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;The Study&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Clance and Imes studied 150 highly successful women for 5 years. They defined highly successful women as PhDs in various specialties, respected professionals in their fields, and students with high honors at prestigious institutions. All of these women shared in common a lack of an internal sense of success. Many believed their accomplishments were a result of luck, and in some cases, they even believed they got into an excellent school or got a great job as a result of some clerical error.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The study noted some clinical symptoms that commonly accompany the impostor phenomenon:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Lack of self-confidence&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Depression&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Frustration, caused by not being able to meet one's own impossibly high standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-gulp.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, looking anxious with the word GULP written underneath&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: Gulp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Contributing Factors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Clance and Imes highlighted four contributing factors to the phenomenon. They first outlined two common family dynamics their subjects experienced as children. The first was being considered &quot;sensitive&quot; or &quot;charming&quot; in comparison to an &quot;intelligent&quot; sibling. These children tended to work hard to prove themselves, but their families remained comparatively unimpressed. They constantly battled between seeking validation and fearing that their family was right after all.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  On the other hand, other subjects experienced the problem of being considered perfect, or effortlessly talented. These children were often told that they had an innate ability that allowed perfection to come easily to them. So, any difficulties the did encounter seemed to be evidence that they were actually none of what they had been propped up to be.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-one-job.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a trophy with a person smacking their hand against their head. The plaque reads: You Had One Job&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: &quot;You Had One Job&quot; Trophy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  The researchers also laid out some societal factors that could contribute to the impostor phenomenon. First, they cited research claiming that women are more likely than men to have low expectations for success in various tasks. Our expectations color our perception of our experiences. When a person experiences unexpected success, they are more likely to attribute that success to an external, temporary cause, such as luck. In contrast, a person who expects to succeed will typically associate that success with an internal, stable cause, such as ability. Additionally, research at the time pointed to low expectations of women by society at large. All of these factors converge and lead to what we now refer to as Impostor Syndrome.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-i-suck.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, frowning and holding a sign that says, I suck&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: I Suck&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Therapies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Clance and Imes also recommended several therapies for their clients in the study:
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;One is &lt;strong&gt;group therapy&lt;/strong&gt; with other high achievers all experiencing the impostor phenomenon. First, this allows clients to see that they are not alone. Also, it may be easier to recognize the intelligence and talent in another person, and to then see the disconnect between reality and that person's self-perceptions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Another suggested therapy is to work on &lt;strong&gt;interrupting ritualistic behaviors&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, when studying for a test, try thinking, &quot;I will do well on this exam,&quot; instead of, &quot;I may fail.&quot; When our success is not consistently preceded by self-doubt, we can break the pattern of predicting failure.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The next recommendation is to think of the people you believe you have fooled, then &lt;strong&gt;imagine confessing to them how you conned them&lt;/strong&gt;. Next, imagine out loud how each person would respond to this news. The authors gave a few examples: &quot;I did not give you an award in English because you charmed me. I did like you as a person, but I honored you for your outstanding work.&quot; &quot;I'm angry that you think I'm so stupid that I can't judge competence when I see it.&quot; &quot;I don't like your negating me and my opinions.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Another recommended therapy is to &lt;strong&gt;keep a record of positive feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. It's important to note also how we deflect this feedback. Eventually, the work is to take in and accept positive feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The authors also suggest a role-playing exercise in which clients &lt;strong&gt;act out the opposite of their negative thoughts about themselves&lt;/strong&gt;. They are to take on a persona who is intelligent, talented, and accomplished, expressing these things out loud. Clance and Imes found that those most resistant to this exercise usually had the most to gain from it. They also noted that it can be especially helpful to do in a group therapy setting, in which the audience responds positively to the self-affirmation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Finally, Clance and Imes encouraged their clients to &lt;strong&gt;try being themselves&lt;/strong&gt; more often. The hope is to disrupt the behavior of doing or saying things we don't want to for the sole purpose of gaining approval from others. Clients are then surprised and encouraged when the catastrophic consequences they imagined never come. Additionally, they are more inclined to accept compliments as authentic when they are being their genuine selves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Limitations&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Of course, there were several limitations to the study as well. The authors noted that more study on men is needed. They found that men experienced the impostor phenomenon less frequently and less intensely than women. Speaking of which, there is also a large focus on the gender binary in the study. It discusses women in contrast to men, and acknowledges no other genders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  It's also important to note that this study comes from a white perspective: both researchers and nearly all participants were white. In the late 1970s, there was a movement to study gender in psychology, and a movement to study race in psychology. But it wasn't until 1989 that the concept of &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality&quot;&gt;intersectionality&lt;/a&gt; (the compounded effects of having multiple marginalized identities) came onto the scene. The term was coined by Kimberlé Williams Crenshaw.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  We also know now that Impostor Syndrome can impact people from all kinds of marginalized groups, be they trans, nonbinary, queer, Latinx, Muslim, neurodivergent, or disabled. And, of course, regardless of frequency or intensity, we know that white men with none of these marginalized identities can experience Impostor Syndrome as well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Normalizing Impostor Syndrome&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Before we dig into how to fight off Impostor Syndrome, I think it's worthwhile to take a moment to normalize this experience. It's not just you!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-same.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, pointing to themself. The text above says, Same&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: Same&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  In the name of normalization, I'll tell you a quick story about my own most recent experience with Impostor Syndrome. When I decided I wanted to start speaking at conferences, I read somewhere that you need to apply to ten conferences to get accepted to one. Of course, I assumed my conference acceptance rate would be lower than average. So, I applied to 40, hoping to get two.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  But instead of having half the rate I'd read about, my acceptance rate was &lt;em&gt;double!&lt;/em&gt; In fact, I had to turn down other conferences in order to give my talk on Impostor Syndrome. And so, thanks to my own Impostor Syndrome, I'm an overbooked pregnant lady! I'm not sure if you can tell as you're reading this, but I'm exhausted!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Beyond my own personal story, Impostor Syndrome affects people at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; levels of their careers. CEOs are just as likely to experience Impostor Syndrome as individual contributors. It's important to remember that &lt;strong&gt;experiencing Impostor Syndrome is not at all an indication that a person is untalented or undeserving of their successes.&lt;/strong&gt; In fact, there are lots of notable badasses who have described their own Impostor Syndrome publicly. Here are some quotes from just a few of them:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  You will never climb career mountain and get to the top and shout, &quot;I made it!&quot; You will rarely feel done or complete or even successful. Most people I know struggle with that complicated soup of feeling slighted on one hand and like a total fraud on the other.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Amy Poehler, decorated actress, director, producer, and writer (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instyle.com/celebrity/stars-imposter-syndrome&quot;&gt;InStyle&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  No matter what we've done, there comes a point where you think, &quot;How did I get here? When are they going to discover that I am, in fact, a fraud and take everything away from me?&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Tom Hanks, award-winning actor and director (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instyle.com/celebrity/stars-imposter-syndrome&quot;&gt;InStyle&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  I have written eleven books, but each time I think, &quot;Uh oh, they're going to find out now. I've run a game on everybody, and they're going to find me out.&quot;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Maya Angelou, author and Nobel Laureate (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/author/quotes/3503.Maya_Angelou?page=9&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Now that you know you're not alone, hopefully you're ready to start taking Impostor Syndrome head on. In the rest of the series, we'll talk about ways to recognize when Impostor Syndrome may be sneaking up on us, and perhaps most importantly, how to fight it!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Thanks for reading! For the rest of the series, check out the next two posts:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html&quot;&gt;Part II: Warning Signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Special thanks to all the people who made and released these awesome resources for free:
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Images by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bitmoji.com/&quot;&gt;Bitmoji app&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/bitmoji/bfgdeiadkckfbkeigkoncpdieiiefpig&quot;&gt;Chrome plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Impostor Syndrome definition paraphrased from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Research by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;Pauline Rose Clance, Ph.D., ABPP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Kimberlé Crenshaw on intersectionality by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality&quot;&gt;Columbia Law School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Quotations by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instyle.com/celebrity/stars-imposter-syndrome&quot;&gt;InStyle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/author/quotes/3503.Maya_Angelou?page=9&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to Part I of a three-part series on Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast. In this section, we will discuss the origin of the term and the initial research carried out on Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series: Part I: Origin Story Part II: Warning Signs Part III: Fight Scene</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;
  Welcome to Part II of a three-part series on &lt;em&gt;Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast&lt;/em&gt;. In this section, we will go over some of the ways to recognize Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part I: Origin Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Part II: Warning Signs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This series is adapted from a talk I gave in 2019 at &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.musiccitytech.com/&quot;&gt;Music City Tech&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://fallexperiment.com/creamcitycode/&quot;&gt;Cream City Code&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://techbash.com/&quot;&gt;TechBash&lt;/a&gt;. You can find the slides from that talk &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/tinezekis/impostor-syndrome-slaying-the-beast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and you can watch the talk I gave at TechBash &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1ABv-toKt2Y&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  If you have not yet read Part I of this series, you can check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Impostor Syndrome: Warning Signs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So, let's get into something practical. How can we recognize Impostor Syndrome when it starts to sneak up on us? Here are some &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.powerofpositivity.com/11-signs-you-have-impostor-syndrome-and-how-to-fix-it/&quot;&gt;warning signs&lt;/a&gt; that you might be experiencing Impostor Syndrome:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-magnifying-glass.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, looking through a magnifying glass&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: Magnifying Glass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You have difficulty accepting praise.&lt;/strong&gt; Lots of people feel weird getting compliments, but &quot;impostors&quot; have trouble even recognizing praise as valid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're an over-worker.&lt;/strong&gt; Perhaps you keep working on a project until it is well beyond the level that the average person would deem acceptable.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You feel the need to be the best.&lt;/strong&gt; Many &quot;impostors&quot; were high achieving as children, and as adults feel compelled to compete when they get into new situations and surround themselves with other smart and talented people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're described as a perfectionist.&lt;/strong&gt; We &quot;impostors&quot; often hold ourselves to impossible standards of perfection. Anything short of this is considered a failure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The fear of failure can paralyze you.&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever opted not to try something, in order to avoid the possibility of failing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You avoid showing confidence.&lt;/strong&gt; This one is more common among people from marginalized genders. This avoidance can come from a fear of appearing to overcompensate, or from a fear of not being able to measure up to expectations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You actually dread success.&lt;/strong&gt; Not feeling worthy of success can lead us to feelings of guilt when we are acknowledged or rewarded for it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You compare your struggles and obstacles to those of others.&lt;/strong&gt; Everyone compares themselves to others, but &quot;impostors&quot; constantly tell themselves that everyone else is getting by with fewer struggles in life than they are.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You associate praise with charm over actual talent.&lt;/strong&gt; Because people with Impostor Syndrome are typically highly intelligent and good at interacting with others, people often find them charming. It is then easy to associate any praise from supervisors or other authority figures as a result of that charm, rather than of our intellect, talent, or hard work.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You focus more on what you &lt;em&gt;haven't&lt;/em&gt; done.&lt;/strong&gt; Going back to that impossible standard of perfection, it's often difficult for us to meet our goals or milestones according to our own expectations. So instead of focusing on our many accomplishments, we tend to dwell on what we haven't done, or what we haven't done &quot;well enough&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You're convinced you aren't enough.&lt;/strong&gt; This last one tends to cut pretty deep. This is about that overwhelming feeling of being a fraud - the fear that one day, everyone will realize you're not everything they thought you were. It's the feeling that you are less qualified than your peers, or that you lucked into where you are today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I also highly recommend the Impostor Syndrome quiz in &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Successful-without-Hurting-Mens-Feelings/dp/1449476074/ref=sr_1_1?crid=1L6111C5LIPFV&amp;keywords=how+to+be+successful+without+hurting+men%27s+feelings&amp;qid=1576890836&amp;sprefix=how+to+be+success%2Caps%2C159&amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Sarah Cooper's &lt;em&gt;How to Be Successful without Hurting Men's Feelings: Non-threatening Leadership Strategies for Women&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of the chapter on Ambition, Cooper includes a 7-question quiz to determine whether you have &amp;mdash; or, perhaps more accurately, the extent to which you have &amp;mdash; Impostor Syndrome. Much like the rest of the book, it's very tongue in cheek. But it does shine a light on the kinds of thinking that you can begin to recognize as your Impostor Syndrome talking. And of course, recognizing these thought patterns is a vital first step in learning to disrupt them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I imagine that you are reading this because you have experienced some amount of Impostor Syndrome in your life. So, now what? It's time for our fight scene! (&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;75%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20191220-impostor-syndrome/bitmoji-fight.png&quot; alt=&quot;Cartoon of a person with brown skin and short, black and pink hair, holding up fists as if to fight&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Bitmoji: Fight&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Thanks for reading! For the rest of the series, check out the other two posts:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-1.html&quot;&gt;Part I: Origin Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2019/12/20/impostor-syndrome-part-3.html&quot;&gt;Part III: Fight Scene&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Credits&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Special thanks to all the people who made and released these awesome resources for free:
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Images by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bitmoji.com/&quot;&gt;Bitmoji app&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/bitmoji/bfgdeiadkckfbkeigkoncpdieiiefpig&quot;&gt;Chrome plugin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Impostor Syndrome definition paraphrased from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Research by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.paulineroseclance.com/pdf/ip_high_achieving_women.pdf&quot;&gt;Pauline Rose Clance, Ph.D., ABPP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Kimberlé Crenshaw on intersectionality by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.law.columbia.edu/pt-br/news/2017/06/kimberle-crenshaw-intersectionality&quot;&gt;Columbia Law School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Quotations by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.instyle.com/celebrity/stars-imposter-syndrome&quot;&gt;InStyle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/author/quotes/3503.Maya_Angelou?page=9&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Impostor Syndrome warning signs by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.powerofpositivity.com/11-signs-you-have-impostor-syndrome-and-how-to-fix-it/&quot;&gt;Power of Positivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to Part II of a three-part series on Impostor Syndrome: Slaying the Beast. In this section, we will go over some of the ways to recognize Impostor Syndrome. Here are the sections for the full series: Part I: Origin Story Part II: Warning Signs Part III: Fight Scene</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Curriculum to Command Line</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/19/curriculum-to-command-line.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Curriculum to Command Line" /><published>2019-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/19/curriculum-to-command-line</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/09/19/curriculum-to-command-line.html">&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;em&gt;This article is adapted from a talk I gave at &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.javascriptandfriends.com/&quot;&gt;JavaScript &amp; Friends&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.musiccitytech.com/&quot;&gt;Music City Code&lt;/a&gt;. You can find the slides from that talk &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/tinezekis/curriculum-to-command-line-why-teachers-make-great-coders-and-what-your-team-can-learn-from-them&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can also read this article on &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://medium.com/@tinezekis/curriculum-to-command-line-why-teachers-make-great-coders-and-what-your-team-can-learn-from-them-2079c533a01a&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;100%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/01-title-page.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Curriculum to Command Line: What teachers make great coders, and what your team can learn from them&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Hello! My name is Christine Zekis, but I go by ‘Tine Zekis, which also happens to be my Twitter handle (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tinezekis&quot;&gt;tinezekis&lt;/a&gt;). My pronouns are she, her, hers. I’m a Software Engineer and a former High School Math Teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Before we dig in, I’d like you to take a moment to consider this question: &lt;em&gt;Who was your favorite teacher and why?&lt;/em&gt; This could be anyone from your preschool teacher to a college professor, or anything in between. And it doesn’t need to be from a traditional education setting…maybe it’s your Sunday school teacher, or a dance instructor, or a soccer coach.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Here’s what I came up with when I did this exercise:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  My favorite teacher was my high school geometry teacher, Ms. Hardin.
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;She had a great sense of humor&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;She was able to break down logic and explain her reasoning&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;She related the content to our lives&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;She was deeply committed to her students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Now that you’ve thought a bit about what makes an awesome teacher, I’d like to spend a few minutes convincing you of my premise…that awesome teachers make awesome coders.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/02-argument.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;The Argument: Why (awesome) teachers make awesome coders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;(Awesome) Teachers Make Awesome Coders&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  While planning any lesson, most teachers will start with the learning objectives. What will students be able to do as a result of this lesson? A learning objective might be something like, “As a student in Ms. Zekis’s Algebra class, I can apply the quadratic formula to solve word problems involving trajectory.” Perhaps you’ve seen something similar in your work, only developers would call this a &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;user story&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. A user story could be, “As a user with admin access, I can edit the names and email addresses of other users.”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/03-user-stories.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;User Stories: What will users be able to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Learning Objectives =&gt; User Stories&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So let’s talk about the learning objectives, or user stories, for this article:
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;As a &lt;strong&gt;programmer&lt;/strong&gt;, I can improve my comprehension and hone my problem-solving skills by creating and taking opportunities to teach others.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;As a &lt;strong&gt;team member&lt;/strong&gt;, I can improve my communication skills by breaking down concepts for a variety of audiences.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;As a &lt;strong&gt;leader&lt;/strong&gt;, I can help my team to become better collaborators by creating a culture of teaching and learning.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;As a &lt;strong&gt;hiring manager&lt;/strong&gt;, I can appreciate the skills that former educators and other career changers may bring to the table.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Consider these various roles and decide what your goals will be for the remainder of your reading here. Try to focus on one or two of these objectives as we continue on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  After establishing the learning objectives, teachers will typically move on to the assessment. How do we know we met our objectives? Translating this to the world of coding isn’t too much of a stretch: this is when we would write our tests or specs. How do we know the code does what we say it does?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/04-write-the-tests.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Write the Tests: How do we know it does what we say it does?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Write the Assessment =&gt; Write the Tests&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  When I used to write math exams, I would start by making sure the students can solve a particular type of problem with an intuitive solution. For instance, the answer is a positive, whole number. Developers might call this the &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;happy path&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. But I also want to make sure the students can solve problems with harder solutions. Maybe the answer is negative, or zero. Maybe it’s a very large number or a decimal. These are our &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;edge cases&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  And not until the assessment is done do I start to figure out what the students must do to get from where they are to where they will need to be to meet the objectives. In education, we call this Backward Planning, or Outcome-Based Education. In the tech industry, we might call this &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;test-driven development (TDD)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Then, after all the planning, it’s time to actually teach the lesson. This is usually around the time that 90% of the plan gets thrown out the window. I’m going to call this part &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;deployment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Throw it out there and wait for something to go wrong.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/05-deployment.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Development: Here goes nothin'!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Teaching the Lesson =&gt; Deployment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Various studies have estimated that teachers make anywhere from 1,000 to 3,000 decisions per day in their classrooms. I’ve seen &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;http://info.csp.edu/globalassets/academic-resources/academic-departments/teacher-education/teacher-education-conceptual-framework.pdf&quot;&gt;1,500&lt;/a&gt; cited most often, so we’ll stick with that for the sake of argument. If we assume a day from 8:00am to 3:00pm with a 30-minute lunch break, that’s more than 230 decisions per hour, which is almost 4 per minute. So that’s a decision just about every 15 seconds. Teachers are constantly adjusting to the changing situations in their classrooms — moving closer to the student who seems distracted, pausing to assess understanding, switching gears if the class isn’t getting it or just seems restless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I’m not sure about you, but that’s the kind of person I want troubleshooting support issues on my team. Plus, who better to have on an Agile team doing CI/CD? Our teams need to be nimble, able to pivot when we get new requirements or feedback from our users. And teachers are trained in that kind of flexibility and willingness to change directions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/06-lifelong-learners.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;Lifelong Learners: Coders are constantly growing, adjusting, and learning new things&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Lifelong Learners =&gt; Lifelong Learners&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  One more transferable skill teachers can bring to development is their commitment to lifelong learning. Teachers are constantly growing, adjusting, and learning new things. I’m not going to change this one. This applies to coders without any updates. Technology is always changing, and to do well in this field, coders need to be constantly growing, adjusting, and learning new things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, let’s bring it back to our initial conversation. Think about that favorite teacher you remembered earlier, and consider this: &lt;em&gt;Would your favorite teacher make a great coder? Why or why not?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Here are some things I came up with when I did this. Reasons a teacher might make a great coder:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Adjusts well to changing situations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Good at predicting what might go wrong&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Enjoys solving interesting problems&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Can break down problems into smaller steps&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Thinks outside the box&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Cares deeply about students — Could this translate to caring for users or teammates?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Maybe your favorite teacher just gave really good hugs. Is that something that could translate to being an empathetic programmer? Or maybe they were really good at calling you out on your bullshit. How could that be useful on an engineering team?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  And now we’ve come to the most important part of this article…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So What?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  What does any of this have to do with you? Well, let’s revisit that last point about teachers and coders: they are both lifelong learners.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I hope we can all agree that, in order to excel in this field, we need to be willing and able to continue learning. Now, there are countless studies on how people learn, but I’m going to go way back to some early thinking on the topic. Aristotle once said, “Teaching is the highest form of understanding.” (&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.teachthought.com/pedagogy/great-best-quotes-about-teaching/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Since then, people have done tons of research on the matter, and this seems to actually be the case.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/20190919-curriculum-to-command-line/07-protege-effect.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;figure-caption&quot;&gt;The Protégé Effect: The improved comprehension experienced as a result of teaching a new concept&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Psychologists call it the &lt;strong&gt;Protégé Effect&lt;/strong&gt;. The Protégé Effect is the improved short-term and long-term comprehension one gets from preparing to teach and carrying out a lesson on a new concept. In other words, if you want to learn something, the best thing you can do is teach it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Some of the statistically significant &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://effectiviology.com/protege-effect-learn-by-teaching/&quot;&gt;results of the effect&lt;/a&gt; include:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increased metacognitive processing&lt;/em&gt; — awareness of your learning process&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increased use of effective learning strategies&lt;/em&gt; — things like organizing the material in a logical way, seeking out key pieces of information or major takeaways, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increased motivation to learn&lt;/em&gt; — people often take their learning more seriously when they’re responsible for educating others, rather than just themselves&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increased feelings of competence and autonomy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improved communication skills, confidence, and leadership ability&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So with all of these benefits, it’s pretty compelling as an advantageous and effective way to learn new things.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Ways to Benefit from the Effect&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  There are multiple ways to experience these benefits. First, you can simply &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;prepare&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to teach the concept. Organize the information, consider the answers to potential questions your audience might ask, etc. Planning the lesson alone has been shown to produce some form of the Protégé Effect.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  You can also &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pretend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to teach the topic. Go through the content out loud, as if you are teaching.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  However, the strongest benefits of the Protégé effect will come if you actually &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;teach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; a lesson on the topic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Ways to Teach&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  There are also lots of ways to teach. One is to &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;give a talk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. You can give a lightning talk, host a lunch &amp; learn, lead a meeting, or put together some other form of group presentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Not a fan of public speaking? No problem! &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write it down&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; instead. You can break down concepts in writing through a blog tutorial, or maybe some detailed documentation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  You can also teach in a one-on-one setting by taking on the role of &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mentor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  And I’m sure you can think of other ways to start teaching. Get creative…maybe you want to do a code demo and post it on YouTube. Just as long as you’re communicating information to an audience of some sort.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;So, What Next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So, what can you do differently this coming Monday? Well, old habits die hard, so I’m going to give you some homework.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What can I teach?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Over the next couple of days, try to think about what kinds of things you can teach. Maybe you want to talk about a fun side project you’re working on, or a new technology you’re considering for your team. Or you could talk about the problem you figured out most recently. I’ve found a good rule of thumb to be that if any problem ends up being more than a quick Google search or visit to StackOverflow to solve, write it down. It’s probably a good candidate for a lightning talk or a blog post.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What else can I do in my current role to engender a culture of teaching and learning?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Additionally, I’d like you to think about what else you can do in your current role to help create a culture of teaching and learning on your team. For instance, my team has a designated time for weekly 5-minute lightning talks, and people can just sign up. We also have bi-weekly tech demos where teams show off something they’ve been working on. Last month, our summer interns got the chance to present a feature they built, which was a great opportunity to showcase their work and answer questions about it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;What Would Teacher Do?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  And finally, I want you to think about what your favorite teacher would do. What’s something that made that teacher awesome? Could you do something similar in your own role?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  My favorite teacher, Ms. Hardin, could always lighten the mood and create a positive environment by telling silly jokes. And I was the person on my team who helped keep up a tradition of starting every day with a Dad joke on Slack.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  So what’s something you can do that your awesome teacher did?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Special thanks to all the people who made and released these awesome resources for free:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Teacher statistics from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;http://info.csp.edu/globalassets/academic-resources/academic-departments/teacher-education/teacher-education-conceptual-framework.pdf&quot;&gt;Concordia University, St. Paul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Aristotle quote from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.teachthought.com/pedagogy/great-best-quotes-about-teaching/&quot;&gt;TeachThought&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Protégé Effect summary by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://effectiviology.com/protege-effect-learn-by-teaching/&quot;&gt;Effectiviology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Presentation template by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.slidescarnival.com/&quot;&gt;SlidesCarnival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">This article is adapted from a talk I gave at JavaScript &amp; Friends and Music City Code. You can find the slides from that talk here. You can also read this article on Medium.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Career Changers &amp;amp; Impostor Syndrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/01/10/career-changers-and-impostor-syndrome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Career Changers &amp; Impostor Syndrome" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/01/10/career-changers-and-impostor-syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2019/01/10/career-changers-and-impostor-syndrome.html">&lt;p&gt;
  On Tuesday, January 8th of this year, I gave my first formal lightning talk! &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://devtogether.co/&quot;&gt;Dev Together&lt;/a&gt; put on a lightning talk event (hosted by &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://about.redshelf.com/&quot;&gt;RedShelf&lt;/a&gt;) around the theme &quot;Your first dev job&quot;. Dev Together posted a &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://devtogether.co/blog/jan-lightning-talks-recap&quot;&gt;recap of the event&lt;/a&gt;, where you can see videos of all eight talks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But for those of you whose learning style gives you a preference for reading information, I’m going to recap my talk here. Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Little about Me&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  My name is Christine Zekis, but I go by ‘Tine Zekis…which also happens to be my &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tinezekis&quot;&gt;Twitter handle&lt;/a&gt;, for those of you who would like to follow me after you read this. My pronouns are she/her/hers. And as you may have correctly guessed, I am a career changer. In my former life, I was a high school math teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;70%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/profile-pic.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I started coding about 4 years ago, and I’m currently working as a mid-level software engineer at an AdTech firm called &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.centro.net/&quot;&gt;Centro&lt;/a&gt; (cough..cough…&lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.centro.net/about/careers/&quot;&gt;we’re hiring!&lt;/a&gt;). So, it wasn’t too long ago that I was in the position of looking for my first dev job. And one of the things I remember most vividly from that experience is:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Impostor Syndrome&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Let’s start with a definition I’m paraphrasing from &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;: Impostor Syndrome is a thought pattern where a person diminishes their own accomplishments, largely attributing their successes to luck. This is paired with a fear of being exposed as a “fraud”, or not as capable as they appear to be. Imposter Syndrome can affect all kinds of people at all different stages of their careers. But I think a group that is especially prone to this type of thinking are career changers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I say this for a variety of reasons. First, it’s tough to be new, especially if you’ve been somewhere where you were an expert. There are going to be times when you feel like you don’t belong in tech. Maybe some of your colleagues have been coding since high school, and you’ve only been coding for six months!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;40%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/worried-face.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  These are all legit concerns. But they don’t tell the whole story. So I want to talk about one strategy you can use when you feel Imposter Syndrome sneaking up on you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ditch the Deficit Mindset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Imposter Syndrome feeds off of the deficit mindset. You know, things like: &quot;I’ve never done this;&quot; &quot;I don’t know how to do that;&quot; &quot;Oh my goodness, people are gonna realize I don’t know what the heck I’m doing!&quot; These are the types of thoughts that breed Imposter Syndrome.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So we’re going to work on ditching the deficit mindset. Let’s stop thinking about what you haven’t done…yet. You bring a wealth of experience no one else on your team has. So think about what your unique talents are. What transferable skills have you honed in your previous experiences? These are the things that will build your confidence, and help you start contributing right away to your team. For example, when I was looking for my first dev job, I thought about what skills I had honed as a math teacher.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;60%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/smiling-office-worker.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  For instance, I can get up in front of a room full of people and give a &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://devtogether.co/blog/jan-lightning-talks-recap#tine-zekis&quot;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt;. I also bring a passion for social justice, which translates well to working in diversity and inclusion efforts in tech. But probably the most important skill I bring is my ability to teach. So the guy next to me has been coding since high school. Well, I’ve been tutoring math since high school. I can take a concept that most people find scary or intimidating — like deriving the quadratic formula or the limitations of a technology my team is considering — and I can explain it at the level of whomever I’m talking to. Not every engineer can do that…but every good dev team sure could use someone who can. In the interview for my first dev job, I told my future boss that I’m a developer who speaks human.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So, What about You?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Maybe you’ve worked in sales, and your new dev team is building a tool for the sales team at your company. My &lt;i&gt;goodness&lt;/i&gt;, who better to have in those meetings than you?! You can help your team to understand the needs of your users, since you’re familiar with the day-to-day of a sales team. And you can help explain the technical stuff in a way your colleagues across the table will understand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/business-meeting.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, so the sales example is awfully specific, and probably doesn’t apply directly to most of you, dear readers. So I’d like you all to take a moment (whether you’re a career changer or not), and think about what specific skills you bring to the table. Take some time to think about your transferable skills. Seriously, do it right now. I’ll give you a moment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
  *                    *                    *
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Perhaps you’re thinking about your experience in customer service, or your excellent communication skills. Maybe you are a musician and you’re great at pattern recognition, or you’ve done work with creative problem-solving. Or maybe your previous work has helped you master the art of persuasion. All of these are invaluable skills to bring to a dev team. Revisit this idea over the next few days and try to come up with one or two unique attributes you can highlight. And if you’re having trouble thinking of anything, consider this:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Being new is an asset, in and of itself. You’re a pair of fresh eyes on the code. You can ask questions that no one else has thought of because “that’s just how we’ve always done things”. You bring your unique experience and perspective into everything you do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;I’ll Leave You with This&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Awesome dev teams, who know what they’re doing, aren’t just looking for a good fit. They’re looking for a good add. They want someone who brings something to the table that they don’t already have.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;80%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/diverse-business-colleagues.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So walk into your interviews knowing that’s you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Walk into your first day on the job knowing that’s you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Then comes the really hard part: walk into all the other days on the job knowing that’s you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If you’re worried this won’t come naturally, I find it’s best to take it at a bit of a strut.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img width=&quot;70%&quot; src=&quot;/imgs/model-strut.gif&quot;&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
  *                    *                    *
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If you want to watch the video, check it out below. And if you’d like, you can follow along with my slides &lt;a target=&quot;blank&quot; href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/tinezekis/career-changers-and-impostor-syndrome-leveraging-your-unique-strengths&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;250&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/8o2tt9dt0Lc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">On Tuesday, January 8th of this year, I gave my first formal lightning talk! Dev Together put on a lightning talk event (hosted by RedShelf) around the theme &quot;Your first dev job&quot;. Dev Together posted a recap of the event, where you can see videos of all eight talks. But for those of you whose learning style gives you a preference for reading information, I’m going to recap my talk here. Enjoy! A Little about Me My name is Christine Zekis, but I go by ‘Tine Zekis…which also happens to be my Twitter handle, for those of you who would like to follow me after you read this. My pronouns are she/her/hers. And as you may have correctly guessed, I am a career changer. In my former life, I was a high school math teacher. I started coding about 4 years ago, and I’m currently working as a mid-level software engineer at an AdTech firm called Centro (cough..cough…we’re hiring!). So, it wasn’t too long ago that I was in the position of looking for my first dev job. And one of the things I remember most vividly from that experience is: Impostor Syndrome Let’s start with a definition I’m paraphrasing from Wikipedia: Impostor Syndrome is a thought pattern where a person diminishes their own accomplishments, largely attributing their successes to luck. This is paired with a fear of being exposed as a “fraud”, or not as capable as they appear to be. Imposter Syndrome can affect all kinds of people at all different stages of their careers. But I think a group that is especially prone to this type of thinking are career changers. I say this for a variety of reasons. First, it’s tough to be new, especially if you’ve been somewhere where you were an expert. There are going to be times when you feel like you don’t belong in tech. Maybe some of your colleagues have been coding since high school, and you’ve only been coding for six months! These are all legit concerns. But they don’t tell the whole story. So I want to talk about one strategy you can use when you feel Imposter Syndrome sneaking up on you. Ditch the Deficit Mindset Imposter Syndrome feeds off of the deficit mindset. You know, things like: &quot;I’ve never done this;&quot; &quot;I don’t know how to do that;&quot; &quot;Oh my goodness, people are gonna realize I don’t know what the heck I’m doing!&quot; These are the types of thoughts that breed Imposter Syndrome. So we’re going to work on ditching the deficit mindset. Let’s stop thinking about what you haven’t done…yet. You bring a wealth of experience no one else on your team has. So think about what your unique talents are. What transferable skills have you honed in your previous experiences? These are the things that will build your confidence, and help you start contributing right away to your team. For example, when I was looking for my first dev job, I thought about what skills I had honed as a math teacher. For instance, I can get up in front of a room full of people and give a presentation. I also bring a passion for social justice, which translates well to working in diversity and inclusion efforts in tech. But probably the most important skill I bring is my ability to teach. So the guy next to me has been coding since high school. Well, I’ve been tutoring math since high school. I can take a concept that most people find scary or intimidating — like deriving the quadratic formula or the limitations of a technology my team is considering — and I can explain it at the level of whomever I’m talking to. Not every engineer can do that…but every good dev team sure could use someone who can. In the interview for my first dev job, I told my future boss that I’m a developer who speaks human. So, What about You? Maybe you’ve worked in sales, and your new dev team is building a tool for the sales team at your company. My goodness, who better to have in those meetings than you?! You can help your team to understand the needs of your users, since you’re familiar with the day-to-day of a sales team. And you can help explain the technical stuff in a way your colleagues across the table will understand. Okay, so the sales example is awfully specific, and probably doesn’t apply directly to most of you, dear readers. So I’d like you all to take a moment (whether you’re a career changer or not), and think about what specific skills you bring to the table. Take some time to think about your transferable skills. Seriously, do it right now. I’ll give you a moment. * * * Perhaps you’re thinking about your experience in customer service, or your excellent communication skills. Maybe you are a musician and you’re great at pattern recognition, or you’ve done work with creative problem-solving. Or maybe your previous work has helped you master the art of persuasion. All of these are invaluable skills to bring to a dev team. Revisit this idea over the next few days and try to come up with one or two unique attributes you can highlight. And if you’re having trouble thinking of anything, consider this: Being new is an asset, in and of itself. You’re a pair of fresh eyes on the code. You can ask questions that no one else has thought of because “that’s just how we’ve always done things”. You bring your unique experience and perspective into everything you do. I’ll Leave You with This Awesome dev teams, who know what they’re doing, aren’t just looking for a good fit. They’re looking for a good add. They want someone who brings something to the table that they don’t already have. So walk into your interviews knowing that’s you. Walk into your first day on the job knowing that’s you. Then comes the really hard part: walk into all the other days on the job knowing that’s you. If you’re worried this won’t come naturally, I find it’s best to take it at a bit of a strut. * * * If you want to watch the video, check it out below. And if you’d like, you can follow along with my slides here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Most Important Question</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/06/05/c9-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Important Question" /><published>2015-06-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-06-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/06/05/c9-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/06/05/c9-questions.html">&lt;h4&gt;Assignment: Cultural Blog | Questions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  For this blog post, I was assigned to research the art of asking good questions in the world of coding. As an educator, I have actually already done a lot of study around asking questions. However, I did find &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/help/how-to-ask&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; very helpful in formatting a good question online. It is certainly possible to ask a question and never receive an answer, or to receive answers that don't help you understand what you were hoping to. For this reason, it will be important to follow these steps to increase the possibility that your question will be answered in a way that is helpful to your needs:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Research&lt;/h4&gt;
    Hopefully, before you are posting your question online, you have already conducted some kind of search for the information yourself. If you keep track of the information you found in this search, you may be able to help others understand what information you are still missing. You may even want to provide links to related questions that remain unanswered.
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Summarize your problem in the title&lt;/h4&gt;
    The people who will potentially respond to your question will be looking at the title to determine whether to keep reading. It is important to make sure that your title is specific enough to draw in someone who has knowledge on the subject. I thought these examples from the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/help/how-to-ask&quot;&gt;stackoverflow&lt;/a&gt; article were excellent, so I stole them:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bad: &lt;/b&gt;C# Math Confusion&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Good: &lt;/b&gt;Why does using float instead of int give me different results when all of my inputs are integers?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bad: &lt;/b&gt;[php] session doubt&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Good: &lt;/b&gt;How can I redirect users to different pages based on session data in PHP?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bad: &lt;/b&gt;android if else problems&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Good: &lt;/b&gt;Why does str == &quot;value&quot; evaluate to false when str is set to &quot;value&quot;?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
    Be sure to include error messages you have come across, key APIs (application program interface), and any unusual situation that makes your question unique from (or similar to) other questions you've seen asked. Also, &lt;b&gt;make sure your spelling, punctuation, and grammar are correct in your title&lt;/b&gt;, since this is the first thing people will see. Finally, if you're having trouble coming up with a summarizing title, you can choose to write this part last; after writing out the longer version, it may become more clear what the focus of your problem should be.
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Describe the problem &lt;i&gt;before&lt;/i&gt; displaying any code&lt;/h4&gt;
    Now is the time to expand on the problem introduced in your title. How did you encounter this problem? What difficulties did you run into while trying to solve the problem?
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Make it possible for others to reproduce the problem&lt;/h4&gt;
    This is where you can include code if that is where your problem lies. Be sure to only include the relevant code. Readers of your question should be able to reproduce the problem with the code you have provided.
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Include all tags that are relevant to your question&lt;/h4&gt;
    The sites that allow you to post coding questions will also have a tagging system you can use to attract users who have knowledge on specific, relevant topics. Make sure you tag the language and API you are using. As you begin adding tags, other related tags may become available. Just make sure that you read the descriptions first if you aren't sure whether they are relevant to your problem. If you want more information on tagging, check out &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/help/tagging&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Proof-read!&lt;/h4&gt;
    Try to read through your question with fresh eyes. See if you can recreate the problem using only the information provided. Also, make sure you are checking for spelling, punctuation, and grammar before you post.
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Post your question and be sure to respond to all feedback&lt;/h4&gt;
    Once you have posted your question, stick around for a bit to see if anyone comments on it. There may be some information missing that people ask for. Try to respond right away by editing the question to include that information. Also, if someone has answered your question, try out their suggestion to see if it works and give them feedback on whether or not it did.
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I hope this has been helpful. Be sure to check in again soon, as I will be revamping the website. I'm also moving into the on-site portion of my program at &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://devbootcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Dev Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt; next week, so get excited! Nine weeks from today, you'll be looking at a full-stack developer. Watch out, world!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Resources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/help/how-to-ask&quot;&gt;How do I ask a good question?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/help/tagging&quot;&gt;What are tags, and how should I use them?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Assignment: Cultural Blog | Questions</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Asymptotes with the Big O</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/31/t8-tech.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Asymptotes with the Big O" /><published>2015-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/31/t8-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/31/t8-tech.html">&lt;h4&gt;Assignment: Technical Blog&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  Let's talk about you and me... Let's talk about all the good things and the bad things that make a method take too long even for a computer! So, let's say we're creating a method for our computer, and we want to know whether our method is efficient. That is to say, if we had a very large input, would the computer be able to return the desired output in a reasonable amount of time? In order to understand the efficiency of a method, let us explore the example of looking up a name in a phone book:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Start from the Very Beginning: My Nanny Says It's the Very Best Place to Start&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Let's say we want to find the phone number for Christine Onayemi in a phone book. For those of you who grew up with the Internet, a phone book is a large book containing listings in alphabetical order by last name, then by first name or initial. Each name then has a phone number and possible a street address. So, if we want to find Christine Onayemi, we would flip to the &lt;b&gt;O&lt;/b&gt; section. But how would we tell out computer how to &quot;flip&quot; to a particular page? Instead, we could ask it to take each name and see if the last name starts with an &quot;O&quot;. If not, then it goes on to the next name. And the next. Finally, when we get to a name that does start with &quot;O&quot;, we need to check whether the second letter is &quot;N&quot;, and so on until we have matched the last name. Then we need to look through the &quot;Onayemi&quot;s to find one whose first name starts with &quot;C&quot;, and so on. As you can imagine, if this is a large phone book, this method will take a lot of time. So let's see if we can make this search more efficient.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Start in the Middle and Go from There&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If we have a phone book of, say, 1,000,000 names, then we can instruct our method to start at the halfway mark. So, we look at the name that is 500,000 in from the beginning and compare this name to &quot;Onayemi&quot;. If this name happens to be &quot;Onayemi, Christine&quot;, then we're done...how lucky! But in the much more likely case that this is not the end of our search, we will use what is called a binary search method to continue. If &quot;Onayemi&quot; comes after our halfway-point name alphabetically, then we move on to the three-fourths mark (half of the second half); if &quot;Onayemi&quot; comes before this name, we look at one-fourth (half of the first half). We continue to halve segments until we get to the name we are looking for. Believe it or not, using this method, in a list of 1,000,000 people, we will only need to halve a segment a maximum of 20 times before we are certain to find the name we are looking for. It seems this method is much more efficient than the first!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  So, if there are several ways to solve the same problem, how can we compare them to determine which is the most efficient? Enter: the big O.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Big O Complexity and Notation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Mathematically speaking, each time we ask a computer to carry out a method, we are initiating an algorithm. The complexity of that algorithm will determine the run-time of the method. In order to compare algorithm complexities, big O notation was developed. With big O notation we express the runtime in terms of &lt;b&gt;&quot;how quickly it grows relative to the input, as the input gets arbitrarily large&quot;&lt;/b&gt; (Parker Phinney, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.interviewcake.com/big-o-notation-time-and-space-complexity&quot;&gt;Interview Cake&lt;/a&gt;). We cannot predict runtime exactly, since there are factors we cannot take into account, such as the processor's speed or whether the computer is running other programs simultaneously. Instead, we think of runtime in terms of how quickly it grows as our inputs get bigger and bigger. For big O notation, we will call our input size &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;. We say that our runtime grows &quot;on the order of the size of the input&quot; [&lt;b&gt;O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;], or &quot;on the order of the square of the size of the input [&lt;b&gt;O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;], etc. In fact, the &quot;O&quot; in big O stands for &quot;order&quot;. It will be important to note, that we are only interested in the highest power (order) of &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;, since these will grow the fastest as our input becomes huge. As we approach this huge input, we will also approach some value for our big O notation. This is why &quot;big O analysis&quot; is sometimes referred to as &quot;asymptotic analysis&quot;. Hopefully this will become more clear with some examples, so let's get to it!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Big O Notation Examples&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Addition Algorithm: Linear Complexity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Let's discuss the algorithm for adding two, multi-digit numbers together. Generally, when we add such numbers, we can line them up by place value and begin to add corresponding pairs of digits from right to left. If a sum for any digit pair is greater than 9, we will carry over the digit in the tens place and add it to the next pair of digits. Using this algorithm, if we are adding two 6-digit numbers, then we will have to add six pairs of digits, and possibly carry a seventh. We will assume that the act of adding is more costly to the runtime than the carrying, so the number of pairs to add will be our focus. If we add two 100-digit numbers together, then we need to compute 100 additions. For two 10,000-digit numbers, we must compute 10,000 additions. In this case, the &lt;b&gt;complexity&lt;/b&gt; of our algorithm is directly proportional to the number of digits, which we will call &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;. This is called &lt;b&gt;O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;, or &lt;b&gt;linear complexity&lt;/b&gt;. The algorithm for subtraction would create a similar result, only we will need to borrow rather than carry digits.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Multiplication Algorithm: Quadratic Complexity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Now let's talk about how we would multiply two, multi-digit numbers. We will line the numbers up in a similar fashion by place value. However, this time, we take each digit from the bottom number and multiply it with each digit in the top number (again, carrying digits beyond the ones place). We repeat this for each digit of the bottom number. So, when multiplying two 6-digit numbers, we need to calculate 36 multiplications! There will also be addition of the resulting numbers, but in this case, our multiplication will grow our runtime at a faster rate, so we do not bother ourselves with details regarding addition. If we multiply two 100-digit numbers, we must calculate 10,000 multiplications. Since this algorithm scales with &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, we say that it is &lt;b&gt;O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/b&gt;, or &lt;b&gt;quadratic complexity&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Traveling Salesman&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  A common problem in the world of computer science is that of the &lt;b&gt;Traveling Salesman&lt;/b&gt;: There are &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt; number of towns, and each is linked to one or more other towns by a road of a particular distance. The Traveling Salesman must find the shortest route that allows him to visit each town.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Okay, this isn't so bad...let's say there are three towns: A, B, and C. If there is a road between all pairs, then the salesman's options are limited to the following:
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A → B → C&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;A → C → B&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;B → C → A&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;B → A → C&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;C → A → B&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;C → B → A&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
  And since (A → B → C) and (C → B → A) are really the same paths (just in reverse), one member of each reversed pair can be eliminated. Thus, there are only 3 possibilities for our salesman. No problem!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But what happens when we increase &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt; (the number of towns)? With 4 towns, we get 12 possibilities, 5 towns give 60, 6 towns give 360. We can calculate the number of possibilities by taking half of the factorial of &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;.
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;3! / 2 = 3 * 2 * 1 / 2 = 6 / 2 = 3&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;4! / 2 = 4 * 3 * 2 * 1 / 2 = 24 / 2 = 12&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;5! / 2 = 5 * 4 * 3 * 2 * 1 / 2 = 120 / 2 = 60&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;6! / 2 = 6 * 5 * 4 * 3 * 2 * 1 / 2 = 720 / 2 = 360&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;...&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;25! / 2 = 25 * 24 * … * 2 * 1 / 2 = 15,511,210,043,330,985,984,000,000 / 2 = 7,755,605,021,665,492,992,000,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;b&gt;By the time we get to only 200 towns, we no longer have enough time in the universe to solve this problem with traditional computers!&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Naming Complexities&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Constant Complexity: O(1)&lt;/b&gt; - 1 item takes 1 second, 10 items takes 1 second, 100 items takes 1 second. The input size does not impact the runtime as it grows.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Linear Complexity: O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/b&gt; - 1 item takes 1 second, 10 items takes 10 seconds, 100 items takes 100 seconds. The input and runtime have a linear relationship; as one increases by a factor of 10, so does the other.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Quadratic Complexity: O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/b&gt; - i item takes 1 second, 10 items takes 100 seconds, 100 items takes 10,000 seconds. The runtime grows with the square of the input.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Polynomial Complexity: O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;a&lt;/sup&gt;)&lt;/b&gt; - Any complexity that can be written in this form has a polynomial complexity, or is solvable in &lt;b&gt;polynomial time&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Logarithmic Complexity: O(log &lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;)&lt;/b&gt; - 1 item takes 1 second, 10 items takes 2 seconds, 100 items takes 3 seconds, 1,000 items takes 4 seconds, etc. The number of seconds is the exponent in this relationship, or more precisely, the runtime grows with the log of the input.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Factorial Complexity: O(&lt;i&gt;n&lt;/i&gt;!)&lt;/b&gt; - The runtime grows with the factorial calculation of the input (see the Traveling Salesman example above).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Well, I hope this has been helpful in your understanding of big O complexities and notation, as well as how we determine the efficiency of a method. Please stay tuned as I continue to blog about my learnings at &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://devbootcamp.com/&quot;&gt;Dev Bootcamp&lt;/a&gt;. I'm coming up on my last week before the on-site portion of the program, so get excited!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Resources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/487258/plain-english-explanation-of-big-o&quot;&gt;Plain English Explanation of Big O&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.interviewcake.com/big-o-notation-time-and-space-complexity&quot;&gt;Big O Notation: Using Not-Boring Math to Measure Code's Efficiency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Assignment: Technical Blog</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lost in America</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/31/c8-conflict.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost in America" /><published>2015-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/31/c8-conflict</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/31/c8-conflict.html">&lt;h4&gt;Assignment: Cultural Blog | Conflict&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  I've heard that the way we analyze conflicts (both major and minor) in life can be comparable to the way we analyze problems in our code. If we look at the overall problem, we can get swept up in the overall result, anger or frustration in the case of a conflict, unknown broken code in the case of our programming. But if we look deeper at the source of the conflict, or narrow down which pieces of code are or are not working, we can begin to problem-solve. In the name of further exploration of this notion, I will analyze a conflict from my childhood.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  When I was in high school, shortly after receiving my driver's license, I drove some friends to a mall further out into the suburbs than I had previously driven without a parent. I didn't know the way, but my friends told me they could direct me. (Mind you, kids, this was before smart phones with GoogleMaps, or wide-spread cell phone use of any kind.) We went to the mall, had our fun, and on the way out, I wasn't sure which way to turn. A friend said that if I made a left out of the lot at the light, then I would be on 22nd, a road I knew would take me to a familiar route home. However, when we turned, I saw that the street sign said something else. When I asked about this, my friend said, &quot;Oh, well, this turns into 22nd later.&quot; I continued, hoping my friend was right. More time passed than I was comfortable with, but embarrassed that I didn't know the way myself, I said nothing. Eventually, when the road had still not turned into anything familiar, I said something. Long story short, we ended up calling our parents from a pay phone in the next state over before we had clear instructions on how to get home. I was livid. And my brother made fun of me for literally 10 years (until he did something equally, if not more, embarrassing).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  If I analyze my emotions further, I was not just angry with my friends for having the instructions wrong, but I was also angry with myself for not knowing where I was going. Why had I trusted people whose navigation skills I knew nothing about? Why hadn't I looked up directions beforehand and gotten the feel for a map of the area on my own? Why didn't I say anything as soon as things started to feel off? By the end of the evening, my friends and I were all yelling at each other. I also realize now that anger wasn't the only emotion I was feeling. Part of yelling at them, showing my anger, was to hide the other underlying emotion: fear. Where were we? What if we never figured out how to make it home? What if something terrible happened to us and no one knew where we were?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Eventually, we had to work together to figure out where we were so we could describe it to a parent on the phone. Additionally, we had to work out whose parents would be the most likely to be helpful and not just completely worried and/or angry themselves. We also had to provide phone numbers to those parents so they could let the other parents know what was going on. We learned a lot that night. We also tried tracing our journey on a map later, and my sense of local geography had never been better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  But on a more personal note, &lt;i&gt;I&lt;/i&gt; learned a lot that night about myself and how I deal with others. I learned that I need to be self-reliant, first and foremost, when it comes to my own safety. For instance, even after getting an iPhone, I still look up directions before I go to a new place and make sure that I have a general understanding of where I'm going and how to get back. Also, when I am feeling uncomfortable in a situation, especially with close friends, I speak up. I have learned to trust my intuition, rather than worrying about seeming stupid or unsure.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Assignment: Cultural Blog | Conflict</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">It’s All about Me</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/25/c7-values.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It's All about Me" /><published>2015-05-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-05-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/25/c7-values</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/cultural/2015/05/25/c7-values.html">&lt;h4&gt;Assignment: Cultural Blog | Values&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  In &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://tinezekis.github.io/blog/cultural/2015/05/18/c6-stereotype-threat.html&quot;&gt;last week's cultural blog post&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed Stereotype Threat and its potential to ... One potential tool for battling Stereotype Threat is to &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/reduce.html#encouragingself&quot;&gt;encourage self-affirmation&lt;/a&gt; in those at risk. So, as we approach the on-site portion of the Dev Bootcamp program, we have been asked to engage in a self-affirmation activity related to exploring our values.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  After sifting through an extensive list of values and ranking their importance in my own life, I have decided to focus on personal growth/development. For the last five and a half years, I have made an explicit effort to keep this value at the forefront of my mind and to have it guide my day-to-day actions and long-term life goals. Along with some close friends, I have defined what kind of &quot;grown-up&quot; I want to be. It is not an end goal, but rather a life-long journey of self improvement. Each year, we make year-long goals that will help us to move forward along this journey. And each month, we get together to review the previous month, re-examine our year-long goals, and create goals for the upcoming month. This has given me a sense of accountability to make sure that I am always working actively on improving myself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  People have often asked me about my weight loss secret, as I have lost almost 30 pounds in the last year and a half. They are usually quite disappointed when I say that I did it with hard work: changing my eating and exercise habits a little bit at a time. They usually want to hear that I took some pill or joined some program that made it easy, and fast. It's not fast. When I lose weight fast, I gain it even faster. This last one has been a mission to lose weight slowly, intentionally. My goal is to lose 20 pounds each year for 3 years. And each month, I evaluate how I'm doing and what small, attainable changes I can make. I found that I can take this approach in almost everything I do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  I can definitely see myself using this value as a combatant to Stereotype Threat. The thought that as a black woman, I might not be as good as others at coding is ridiculous to me. Since I am constantly working to improve myself, I have records of an incredible list of accomplishments. I know that, while in the real world, it may seem like I am in competition with others, the only competition I truly value is that with myself. And I am just trying to be a better me today than I was yesterday. That much, I can do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Resources:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/reduce.html#encouragingself&quot;&gt;ReducingStereotypeThreat.org: What Can Be Done to Reduce Stereotype Threat? - Encouraging Self-Affirmation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Assignment: Cultural Blog | Values</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lost in Translation?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/24/t7-JavaScript.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost in Translation?" /><published>2015-05-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2015-05-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/24/t7-JavaScript</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/technical/2015/05/24/t7-JavaScript.html">&lt;h4&gt;Assignment: Technical Blog | JavaScript&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
  This week at Dev Bootcamp, we started learning a new language: JavaScript. There are many similarities between JavaScript and Ruby, as well as many important differences. As with the study of any two languages, it is important to understand which pieces can be translated literally, and which pieces run the risk of getting lost in translation. In order to explore some of these further, we will focus on just one concept in each language. In this post, we will discuss Ruby Hashes and JavaScript Objects.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Ruby Hashes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In Ruby, a hash is a data-storage class. It is similar to an array in that it can store multiple items. However, unlike in the array, the order of these items is unimportant. This means that we do not reference items within a hash by their ordinal location. Instead, all items in a hash are arranged into key/value pairs. Each key points to a corresponding value. For example, if I wanted to keep track of abbreviations for elements of the periodic table, I could create a hash. Each element would be a key with its corresponding abbreviation as the value:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;periodic_abbrevs = {&quot;Hydrogen&quot; =&gt; &quot;H&quot;, &quot;Oxygen&quot; =&gt; &quot;O&quot;, &quot;Carbon&quot; =&gt; &quot;C&quot;, &quot;Zinc&quot; =&gt; &quot;Zn&quot;,&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &quot;Gold&quot; =&gt; &quot;Au&quot;, &quot;Copper&quot; =&gt; &quot;Cu&quot;, &quot;Magnesium&quot; =&gt; &quot;Mg&quot;}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  For all you science buffs out there, you have probably noticed that the elements in this hash are not presented in order according to the periodic table. This does not matter, as for our purposes, we will only need to access an abbreviation (value) by it's element name (key), not by where it falls on the table of elements. If we want to print to the console the abbreviation for Gold, we can do so thusly:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;puts periodic_abbrevs[&quot;Gold&quot;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;samp&gt;=&gt; Au&lt;/samp&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  You have probably also noticed that our hash is not exhaustive. There are still many more elements in the periodic table. Fortunately, we can easily add or remove key/value pairs to a hash. If we want our hash to include phosphorus, for instance, here's how we add it:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;periodic_abbrevs[&quot;Phosphorus&quot;] = &quot;P&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;samp&gt;=&gt; {&quot;Hydrogen&quot; =&gt; &quot;H&quot;, &quot;Oxygen&quot; =&gt; &quot;O&quot;, &quot;Carbon&quot; =&gt; &quot;C&quot;, &quot;Zinc&quot; =&gt; &quot;Zn&quot;, &quot;Gold&quot; =&gt; &quot;Au&quot;,&lt;/samp&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;samp&gt;     &quot;Copper&quot; =&gt; &quot;Cu&quot;, &quot;Magnesium&quot; =&gt; &quot;Mg&quot;, &quot;Phosphorus&quot; =&gt; &quot;P&quot;}&lt;/samp&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  A hash is like an algebraic function in that multiple keys may point to equivalent values, but a single key cannot point to more than one value. In other words, each input must have only one output. To give another example, let's say that we are keeping track of the ages of children at a daycare. The following hash would work just fine:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ages = {sarah: 3, johnny: 4, mary: 4, andy: 3, henry: 4, sally: 3}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  It is perfectly alright for several of these children to be the same age; their name keys can point to equivalent values. However, we cannot have one name point to two different ages:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ages = {sarah: 3, sarah: 4, johnny: 4 ... etc.} &lt;/code&gt;&lt;samp&gt;# unacceptable hash&lt;/samp&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  If there are really two Sarahs at this daycare, then they must have different names for their keys. Perhaps &lt;code&gt;sarah_jones&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sarah_smith&lt;/code&gt;. Otherwise, how can the program know which value to access for that key? Please note that if you add an existing key to a hash, it will overwrite the existing key/value pair, replacing the previous value with the new one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;JavaScript Objects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  In JavaScript, an object is a wrapped collection of properties. Perhaps we have several musicians which each have a name, instrument, and genre. We would store this information into various &lt;code&gt;Musician&lt;/code&gt; objects thusly:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function Musician(name, instrument, genre) {&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  this.name = name;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  this.instrument = instrument;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  this.genre = genre;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;var yoYoMa = new Musician(&quot;Yo-Yo Ma&quot;, &quot;cello&quot;, &quot;Classical&quot;)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  Later, if I need to access the instrument Yo-Yo Ma plays, I can simply call for his instrument property:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;yoYoMa.instrument;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;samp&gt;=&gt; cello&lt;/samp&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  Additionally, I can add and remove properties from an object. For instance, we can add a famous Yo-Yo Ma quote to the &lt;code&gt;yoYoMa&lt;/code&gt; object thusly:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;yoYoMa.quote = &quot;I think one of the great things about being a musician&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;  is that you never stop learning.&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Key Points for Translation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  As you have likely noticed, hashes in Ruby and objects in JavaScript have many similarities. The properties of an object have names and associated values, much like the key/value pairs of a hash. We can access these values at any time by referencing their names or keys. We can also add and remove properties or key/value pairs. So, if I were translating a hash from Ruby into JavaScript, I would likely use an object. But be careful, because these two things are not identical!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  First, as we have seen from our examples, we do not construct these things in the same way in the two languages. The syntax is quite different. Additionally, Ruby and JavaScript have multiple ways to create and build onto hashes and objects, respectively. Trying to use the syntax of one in the other language would create several errors.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
  Another word of caution has to do with the English language. In Ruby, there are also such things as objects, and they can be quite different from hashes. In fact, a hash is just one type of &lt;i&gt;infinitely many&lt;/i&gt; objects in Ruby, since we can invent our own classes to create new types of objects all the time. So, while it is important to note these similarities for ease of understanding, we must not be too quick to equate them.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>'Tine Zekis</name></author><summary type="html">Assignment: Technical Blog | JavaScript</summary></entry></feed>